Okay so we pick up today with on דף ל"ו עמוד ב'
beis. *Daf Lamed Vav Amud Bet*, ת"ש ל"ז *Tash Lamed Zayin*, but
a little behind. And we're in the middle of discussing whether night
is a time for wearing תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin*, where the what do
you call it, where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* introduced a couple of
opinions when you have to take it off: as soon as the
sun sets, which is halachic night, or ספק safek. *Safek* night, or
when people start, you know, are done commuting back from work, תכלה
רגל מן השוק *Tichleh Regel Min Hashuk*, or it's time for sleeping.
The last two are not halachic definitions of night or day. The
last two are a what do you call it, the last two
are a concern for maybe it's time for sleeping. Oh, there we
go.
Let's look at that.
Okay. So the last two concerns are an issue about maybe people
are going to sleep, which is not a halachic issue about whether
night is a time for תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin*, it's rather a concern
about you might fall asleep which is a rabbinic concern and then
you'll come to pass gas.
So that's the issue about whether in principle לילה לאו זמן תפילין
lailah lav zeman tefillin, *Laila Lav Zman Tefillin*.
We will see in a minute why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* might
say yes or no.
What I don't understand was the concern that night you're going to
pass gas and not the whole rest of the day?
In the rest of the day you're awake and you can control
yourself. And if you're about to pass gas, you take off your
תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. Then you need to go out and take off
your תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* lest you don't control, or if
you fall asleep, you might fall asleep.
Thank you, that's the point, might fall asleep. Okay, so the interesting
thing and even though we'll see in a minute is, although night
is not the time for תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*, right, why that leads
to an actual prohibition to continue to wear it? Is it like,
you know, I mean there's a lot of things that are not
a מצווה *Mitzvah* at night. It's not a מצווה *Mitzvah* to take
לולב *Lulav* at night. Is it אסור assur, *Assur* for me to
hold on to my לולב *Lulav* at night? It might be a
type of בל תוסיף *Bal Tosef* concern, you know, if you're holding
on to your לולב *Lulav* at night because you're it's part of
an act of doing a מצווה *Mitzvah*, then there may be a
problem about בל
תוסיף *Bal Tosef*.
Or ציצית tzitzis *Tzitzis*.
Right, so that's also a question about ציצית tzitzis *Tzitzis* is an
excellent example where we're not מקפיד *Makpid* to tear off our ציצית
Tzitzit *Tzitzis* although there's debate maybe I am חייב chayav. *Chayav* at
night is it מצוות בגד יום yom, *Mitzvas Beged Yom*. But anyway,
part of it part of it might be yes, some type of
בל תוסיף *Bal Tosef* issue, but part of it also might be
what do you call it, that it's that even the תורה Torah
*Torah*'s issue about it's a מצווה *Mitzvah* only in the day and
not at night, you know, either you could connect it to some
of these issues about awareness, you know I wouldn't necessarily say passing
gas, but consciousness and awareness. We're going to see the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* compares the whole thing to the ציץ tzitz *Tzitz*. So that's
on the one hand. And the other issue I would say is
and this goes to the larger thing that we've been discussing about
a question about an action וקשרתם Ukishartam, *Ukshartem* as opposed to a
state והיו Vehayu, *V'hayu*. And it could be that, you know, if
there's like a sort of a state of being that maybe the
תורה Torah *Torah* is like defining,
you know, parameters that it sort of there's a starting point and
an ending point, meaning as opposed to as opposed to, you know,
if you were to like not have a time where if if
you could do it sort of at all times, it's almost the
problem of like creating קדושה *Kedusha*. You need boundaries to it, right?
If it's sort of everywhere then it doesn't have those boundaries it
doesn't have that status. So anyway, it is interesting to dismiss this
issue. It is דף ל"ז *Daf Lamed Zayin* that if לילה לאו
זמן תפילין Layla lav zman tefillin... *Laila Lav Zman Tefillin* all of
a sudden there's an assumption in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that there's
a חיוב Chiyuv, *Chiyuv* to take off your תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* as
soon as it becomes night. And Michael says Madi's contrast to that
is ציצית Tzitzit *Tzitzis*. But let's continue with that now in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Did you discuss the women's issue?
No, women's issue does not come up here. You're right logically about
whether לילה layla *Laila* is זמן zeman. *Zman* make the question about
מצוות עשה mitzvos asseh שהזמן גרמא *Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Grama*. This גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* doesn't address itself to it. עירובין *Eruvin* is one of
the major גמרות *Gemoros* that this discusses in wearing תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*.
It doesn't come up in this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay so גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
where were we? הא היא פליגי *Ha Hi Pligi*. Two lines from
the bottom. Two lines from the top הלוואי *Halevai*. ומי אמר רבה
בר רב הונא Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna: הכי *Umi Amar Rabbah
Bar Rav Huna Hachi*? Did רבה בר רב הונא *Rabbah Bar Rav
Huna* really say that, that you know you could wear תפילין tefillin
*Tefillin* if you had them on during the day you could keep
on wearing them at night? והאמר רבה בר רב הונא ספק safek
חשיכה ספק safek. לא חשיכה לא חולץ ולא מניח *V'ha-amar Rabbah Bar
Rav Huna Sfeik Chasheicha Sfeik Lo Chasheicha Lo Choleitz V'lo Maniach*. If
it's בין השמשות *Bein Hashmashos*, you don't have to take it off
but you're not allowed to put on your תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*, which
implies הא ודאי חשיכה *Ha Vaddai Chasheicha*,
definitely night, חולץ *Choleitz* you have to take it off. So how
did he keep on wearing his תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* when it came
time to דאווען מעריב *Daven Maariv* which was the story we said
at the end of yesterday? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says התם
בערב שבת Shabbos. אתמר *Hatam B'erev Shabbos Itmar*. There it was said
by ערב שבת Shabbos, *Erev Shabbos*, meaning when do you have to
take it off when it's definitely night? When it's Friday night. Because
then it's not just about wearing your תפילין Tefillin *Tefillin* at night,
it's about wearing your תפילין Tefillin, *Tefillin* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So
what he's going by
is that שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* is everybody
agrees is לאו זמן תפילין Lav zman tefillin, *Lav Zman Tefillin*. And
therefore or, you know, and therefore even if so even if going
into night is זמן תפילין zman tefillin. *Zman Tefillin* מדאורייתא *Midoraisa* and
it's just a concern of passing gas, so he's more lenient if
you're already wearing it, but when it comes to שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*,
that clearly is לאו זמן תפילין Lav zman tefillin, *Lav Zman Tefillin*
and he would agree you would have to take it off Friday
night once it's ודאי *Vaddai* night.
But it can't mean that it's not זמן תפילין zman tefillin, *Zman
Tefillin* you don't have to like put it on but if you
had it on from before.
Right, that's what I said. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming לאו
זמן Zman תפילין Tefillin, *Lav Zman Tefillin* if it's מדאורייתא *Midoraisa* means
you have to take it off. So let's take the what. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. התם בערב שבת Shabbos, אתמר
*Hatam B'erev Shabbos Itmar*. There we were talking about Friday night. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute,
מאי קסבר kasavar, *Mai Kasavar*? What does he hold? אי קסבר לילה
layla לאו זמן תפילין Tefillin, *Ee Kasavar Laila Lav Zman Tefillin*, שבת
Shabbos נמי *Shabbos Nami*, לילה זמן תפילין Tefillin *Laila Zman Tefillin*, night
is a time where you
can wear תפילין Tefillin, *Tefillin*. Wait, from the same
פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* we
exclude שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, we exclude night. For those that exclude night
and exclude שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, there are opinions that say that שבת
*Shabbos* is זמן תפילין Tefillin *Zman Tefillin*. How do you know this?
דתניא *De-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita *Braisa*, ושמרת את החוקה
הזאת Ve-shamarta es ha-chukkah ha-zos. למועדה מימים ימימה *V'shamarta es hachuka hazos
l'moadah miyamim yamima*, right? By פסח *Pesach*, but it also says one
of the פרשיות *Parshiyos* says it by תפילין Tefillin. *Tefillin*. So keep
the חוק *Chok* from פסח *Pesach* and then it says והיה vehaya,
לאות על ידך al yadecha ולטוטפת בין עיניך bein einecha. *V'haya l'os
al yadecha u-l'totafos bein einecha*, ושמרת Ve-shamarta את החוקה הזאת *V'shamarta es
hachuka hazos*.
So is ושמרת Veshamarta, *V'shamarta* going on פסח *Pesach* or is it
also going on תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*? So and and here it has
the keyword מימים ימימה *Miyamim yamima*, day, okay? So מימים ימימה *Miyamim
yamima*
for the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* or the חוק *Chok* that they
took up, ימים ולא לילות *Yamim v'lo leilos*, days and not nights.
מימים *Miyamim*, some days, ולא כל ימים *v'lo kol yamim*, not all
days, פרט לשבתות וימים טובים *Prat l'shabbosos v'yamim tovim*. So here we're
saying only day and only weekdays, and that's where and this is
being understood about תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. דברי רבי Divrei Rabbi. יוסי הגלילי
*Divrei Rabbi Yosi Ha-Glili*. We have a מחלוקת machloket *Machlokes*, Michael. דברי
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, הגלילי *Divrei Rabbi Yosi Ha-Glili*. רבי Rebbe עקיבא
אומר omer, *Rabbi Akiva Omer*, לא נאמר חוקה זו אלא לפסח בלבד
*Lo ne'emar chuka zu ela l'Pesach bilvad*. No, חוק *Chok* is only
refers to פסח *Pesach*, not referring to תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. Okay, דתניא
*De-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita *Braisa*, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says so you see if you learn the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*
about תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*, it excludes both nighttime and שבת *Shabbos*. We
don't have a split between night and שבת *Shabbos*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says נפקא ליה מהיכא דנפקא ליה לרבי עקיבא *Nafka lei
me-heicha de-nafka lei l'Rabbi Akiva*. No, look, let's take רבי Rabbi. עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva*. רבי Rabbi? עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says the פסוק Pasuk *Pasuk*
isn't talking about תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* still says
that you don't wear תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin* on שבת *Shabbos*. How do
we know it? דתניא *De-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita. *Braisa*,
רבי עקיבא אומר omer *Rabbi Akiva Omer*, the same רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* who denied that that's a פסוק Pasuk *Pasuk* about תפילין tefillin,
*Tefillin* and would say that in theory you could wear תפילין tefillin,
*Tefillin* at night says the following: יכול יניח
אדם תפילין tefillin בשבתות ובימים טובים *Yachol yanich adam tefillin b'shabbosos u-v'yamim
tovim*, maybe you would wear תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin* on שבת *Shabbos* and
יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar. והיה vehayah,
לאות על ידך Yadcha ולטוטפת בין עיניך bein einecha *Talmud lomar v'haya
l'os al yadecha u-l'totafos bein einecha*, the sign on your hand and
טוטפת *Totafos* between your eyes, מי שצריכים אות os *Mi she-tzrichim os*,
only when they're needed to serve as an אות os? *Os*. יצאו
שבתות וימים טובים *Yatzu shabbosos v'yamim tovim*, to exclude שבת *Shabbos* and
יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, שגופם אות os *She-gufam os*, which
themselves serve as an אות os *Os*. And therefore, and therefore you
do not wear it on שבת *Shabbos* although you can wear it
at night. And that was the position of who we started with,
רב הונא *Rav Huna*, who was okay to keep it on at
night but not okay to keep it on Friday night for שבת
*Shabbos*.
How do we know that ימים טובים yamim tovim *Yamim Tovim* are
an אות os *Os*? I know שבת *Shabbos* is...
I will talk about that in a minute. Let's read a little
bit more in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and then I'm going to
get back to some of the interesting things about this. Okay, so
that's how we know to exclude שבת *Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*. And by the way, you know although by night
normally nobody's you know wearing תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* that way in the
day and we're not sensitive to it as much, you know we
take it for granted that by שבת *Shabbos* it's not just you
don't have to wear תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* on שבת *Shabbos* but you're
not allowed to wear תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* on שבת *Shabbos*, right? The
very idea that if it's learned from the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*, it's
really that you're not allowed to is certainly something that we've internalized
when it comes to שבת *Shabbos*. Now again the question is why,
and I think again the point here about the אות os *Os*
is significant. That you know for something to be a sign, if
it's constant, it's not a sign. So the idea is that you
know that you could say no, maybe it undermines the קדושת שבת
*Kedushas Shabbos* that you're saying שבת *Shabbos* is not sufficiently being a
sign so one of the you know one of the functions is
being undermined if you have to do both, that it means neither
is significant by itself. You could frame it like that, that's why
you can't have them both because you're somewhat being פוגע *Pogaya* either
in תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin* or in שבת *Shabbos*. But I also think
that it also even undermines in general the concept of a sign,
gives it some some boundaries, some limits, or else it's just not
a sign, it's just something you're always doing. So I also think
it's interesting, similarly I wrote about this a little in my פרשה
*Parsha* thing that went out yesterday because we're about to compare the
two into the ציץ *Tzitz*. And the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* wears
the ציץ *Tzitz* and he's מקדש *Mikadesh* with the ציץ *Tzitz* and
you wear the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* and you're thinking about God. Okay,
interesting thing though, that when does the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* not
wear the ציץ *Tzitz*? This week's פרשה *Parsha*, עבודת יום הכיפורים *Avodas
Yom HaKippurim*, right? Because he doesn't wear the ציץ *Tzitz*, he does
the בגדי לבן *Bigdei Lavan*. You know why? Because he's going into
the קודש קודשים *Kodesh Kodashim*. You don't even need... I know that.
You don't need a ציץ *Tzitz* if you're going into the קודש
קודשים *Kodesh Kodashim*. ציץ *Tzitz* is to remind you of God. If
you're encountering God, like you don't need the ציץ *Tzitz*. And in
a way that would be a פגיעה *P'gia*. Who's wearing a ציץ
*Tzitz* when you're actually having this other encounter? And that's you know
and so I think that that's a very similar thing. So who
needs the אות os. *Os* of if you're having שבת *Shabbos* itself?
You know who needs the אות os. *Os* of תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*
if you're actually having the encounter of
שבת *Shabbos* itself?
Well, except for night.
Well yes,
but it's not all right. I'll bracket that for that. Anyway, so
that I think is part of what is going on here about
why it's not just you don't have to but not allowed to.
Now the question is to what degree do שבתות וימים טובים *Shabbosos
v'yamim tovim* serve as an אות os *Os*? And the other very
relevant question about this is חול המועד Chol HaMoed. *Chol HaMoed*, which
is big מחלוקת ראשונים Rishonim *Machlokes Rishonim* all the way back whether
the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* here is referring to חול המועד Chol HaMoed,
*Chol HaMoed* or not and there are different it's not discussed in
the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* at all. It's all ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*, it's
all גמרתא *Gemarta*, it's one of the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, yeah. Anyway
and it's until today. So if you take a look at the
first line of the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, three lines down of the
wide lines, ושמרת Veshamarta, את החוקה הזאת למועדה es ha-chukkah ha-zos le-mo'adah,
*V'shamarta es hachuka hazos l'moadah*, בפרק סימנא בסוף פרק Perek, מברך *b'perek
Simana b'sof perek Mevarch*, I'm sorry no, the other תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*,
יצאו שבתות וימים טובים שאין אתם קרויין אות os *Yatzu shabbosos v'yamim
tovim she-ein atem keruyin os*, he says לא משום... לאו משום דאסירי
בעשיית מלאכה. melacha, It's not because of the איסור מלאכה, issur melacha,
which is by the way mean not on יום טוב, Yom Tov.
not on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. The אות os is not because
you don't do מלאכה, melacha, דאפילו חול המועד דשרי בעשיית מלאכה איכא
אות. de-afilu Chol HaMoed de-shari ba-asiyas melacha ika os.
What's the אות? os בפסח דאסור באכילת חמץ be-Pesach de-assur ba-achilas chametz
ובסוכה דחייב בסוכה. u-be-Sukkah de-chayav be-Sukkah.
There are, you know, those מצוות עשה mitzvos asseh that sort of
are memories, make you remember what these
ימים טובים yamim tovim represent. Of course, שבועות Shavuos you don't have
it, but שבועות Shavuos at least has איסור מלאכה. issur melacha. So
תוספות Tosafos here is saying and חול המועד, Chol HaMoed exactly. So
תוספות Tosafos here is saying that the אות os is through, you
know, maybe primarily through the מצוות עשה mitzvos asseh that they remind
you of what the ימים טובים yamim tovim historically represent. And on
שבועות Shavuos it could also be the איסור מלאכה, issur melacha, but
anyway for תוספות Tosafos therefore it includes חול המועד. Chol HaMoed, Other
ראשונים Rishonim of course strongly disagree, different practices. I knew somebody who
when he was going to work on חול המועד Chol HaMoed. would
not would wear תפילין. tefillin And then when he got to a
stage in life where he felt he wasn't going to work anymore
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed? then he stopped wearing תפילין. tefillin So
he actually tied it into the issue of איסור מלאכה, issur melacha,
but that was not what the הלכה halacha of איסור מלאכה issur
melacha but his own personal practice on איסור מלאכה. issur melacha. It's
a serious question. You know, there's strong basis to say either way.
It's
a מצות עשה דאורייתא mitzas asseh de-Oraisa on one hand. On the
other hand, the גמרא Gemara's here by אות os clearly feels we're
דווקא davka not supposed to do the אות os when it's not
the זמן. I grew up with the מנהג minhag not to wear
תפילין tefillin on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed
Then at a certain stage I decided I was going to wear
תפילין tefillin without a ברכה beracha because that way I'm sort of
covering my bases sort of. I'm doing the מצוה, mitzvah, not making
a ברכה, beracha, it's not a ברכה לבטלה. beracha le-vatalah. You could
say maybe it's not so much of a פגם pegam in יום
טוב Yom Tov if you're not making the ברכה beracha because you're
acknowledging the ספק. Of course what winds up happening nine times out
of ten not really, but at least a few times is I
go into autopilot, so as soon as the תפילין tefillin goes on,
the ברכה beracha comes out. Then I have to figure out what
I do when I get to the של ראש. shel rosh. Okay,
anyway.
But the interesting thing though is
the גמרא Gemara would say that the אות os?
is by שבת. Right. It's called an אות. os Right. But תוספות
Tosafos.
is saying it's not.
Well, no, he had to he had to borrow that by שבת,
תוספות Tosafos would have said that, but by the יום טוב Yom
Tov? he's forced to extend the idea. But you're right, the תורה
Torah never just says it by the יום טוב. Yom Tov I
mean it could include שבת with the מועדים, moadim, but normally that's
the other way, that שבת is called a מועד. moed. Right, you
don't really have the ימים טובים yamim tovim being called an אות.
Ot, You sometimes say you have "and you should remember," what does
it say by סוכות? Sukkos? למען ידעו דורותיכם Lema'an yede'u doroseichem no.
כי בסוכות הושבתי את בני ישראל... Ki ba-Sukkos hoshavti es Benei Yisrael...
למען ידעו דורותיכם Lema'an yede'u doroseichem and so on. But you know,
but yeah, it is תוספות Tosafos is saying it because the גמרא
Gemara is saying it. And this idea of applying the idea of
אות Ot, to יום טוב Yom Tov, then forces the ראשונים Rishonim
to think
about what is it sort of conceptually and הלכתית halachically meant for
תוספות. Tosafos So right, does it apply to חול המועד? Chol HaMoed.
What is the אות Ot, aspect of יום טוב?
Which תוספות Tosafos are we saying?
חול המועד Chol HaMoed, you do... He says it goes on to
say go back and forth, but his basic point is to say
you do wear תפילין tefillin, on you don't wear תפילין tefillin, on
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed? The אות os is the מצות היום. mitzas
ha-yom. The special the unique character of the יום, not the איסור
מלאכה. issur melacha. So what are people who say that you do?
What's their... They say it's איסור מלאכה issur melacha based on you
know. Then comes another question: is there איסור מלאכה issur melacha on
חול המועד, and is it דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, is it דרבנן? de-Rabbanan? How
do we understand the איסור מלאכה issur melacha on חול המועד? So
that's that whole discussion.
But you could have said that just applies in כיפור, Kippur, where
you really can't do מלאכה, melacha. but then it shouldn't apply to
ימים טובים because you can do some מלאכה. melacha.
I understand. Okay, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. So you have
to figure out what the גמרא Gemara is talking about.
You implied the אות os as an אות for yourself rather than
an outward sign, which I had somehow always assumed...
Well there is the both. There's והיה לך לאות Ve-hayah lecha le-os
by the של יד shel yad and you know, וראו כל עמי
הארץ, Ve-ra'u kol amei ha-aretz, which is you know they talk about
the של ראש. shel rosh. But the אות is לך לאות. lecha
le-os. But that's a good point, לך לאות,
lecha le-os, like not for other people.
Right. Although certainly other people are sensitized to it. And you know
the מצוות עשה Aseh, have more of a public character than the
passive not
doing מלאכה.
But associated with the idea of תפילין tefillin,
being an אות for others? Right, although again the גמרא Gemara. says
לך לאות ולא לאחרים לאות.
lecha
le-os ve-lo le-acherim le-os.
It's the וראו כל עמי הארץ Ve-ra'u kol amei ha-aretz by the
של ראש, shel rosh, but the של יד shel yad it says
והיה לך לאות, ve-hayah lecha le-os, לך לאות ולא לאחרים לאות, lecha
le-os ve-lo le-acherim le-os, and similar like by דם הפסח, Dam Ha-Pesach,
right? והיה הדם לכם לאות. Ve-hayah ha-dam lachem le-os. So
there's the question about who is right who is paying attention to
the אות?
This refers to the של יד. shel yad.
Right.
It's exactly it. The פסוק pasuk. about אות is דרש darshaned by
the גמרא Gemara והיה לך לאות. ve-hayah lecha le-os. Okay, so that's
that. Now in terms by the way about לילה לאו זמן תפילין,
tefillin תוספות Tosafos from ושמרת Veshamarta quotes the famous ירושלמי Yerushalmi that
says
that in the or גמרא Gemara that let's take a quick look
at that תוספות ושמרת Tosafos Ve-shamarta as well, את החוקה הזאת למועדה,
בפרק הפסים be-Perek Ha-Passim ובפרק כיצד מברכין, u-be-Perek Keitzad Mevarchin, one תוספות
Tosafos up, דאמרינן דבני מערבא מברכי בפוטי דמשלפי תפילייהו,
de-amrinan de-benei ma'arava me-varchi
be-foti de-meshalfi tefilaihu, that the בני מערבא, benei ma'arava, people from the
West, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, after they took off their תפילין tefillin
would make a ברכה לשמור חוקיו. beracha lishmor chukkav. Okay. ברוך אתה
ה' אלקינו מלך העולם אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לשמור חוקיו.
Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha-olam
asher kidishanu be-mitzvosav ve-tzivanu lishmor chukkav. Based on the פסוק pasuk. of
ושמרת את החוקה הזאת. Okay. So
therefore it's a ברכה אחרונה. beracha acharonah. And תוספות Tosafos: says oh
that would probably only be if they took it off when it
was next near nightfall, assuming they would wear תפילין tefillin. through a
lot of the day. So you're taking off... ...taking it off because
nightfall is coming and it's becoming the זמן of לאו זמן תפילין,
tefillin. and it's based on the פסוק pasuk of ושמרת את החקה
הזאת, Veshamarta et hachuka hazot, and you make the ברכה Beracha of
לשמור חקיו. Lishmor Chukav. So earlier, earlier? Well, that's what תוספות Tosafos's
says, he said probably not. Anyway, the interesting thing I think again
about this is exactly that, since when do you have a מצוה,
Mitzvah, like Rabbi Michael said, you make like a ברכה Beracha at
the end, ברכה אחרונה Beracha Acharona at the מצוה? Mitzvah? And again
in my mind this emphasizes the idea of תפילין tefillin. not just
being, you know, the two aspects of it, so there's the מצוה
Mitzvah of וקשרתם, ukshartam, the active, and then there's the והיו, the
state. So the idea of the state is sort of like framing
this as a period or state, so you have it for example,
you have it by שבת, you know, you have קידוש Kiddush and
הבדלה, Havdalah, that's exactly sort of what it is, you know, so
you're entering it in and then you're acknowledging that it's no longer
going to be the time of it. But anyway, that idea of
doing it at the end seems to again reflect this emphasis of
also state of wearing תפילין, tefillin not just the sort of act
of wearing תפילין, tefillin. which also connects to why you might want
to limit that state, you know, for it to be an אות,
you don't want it to be constant. Yes, what were you going
to
say? ברכת התורה, Birchas Hatorah, ברכה אחרונה, Beracha Acharona, you have a
complex ברכה, Beracha, you don't have it sort of at the end
of... well, when you get an עליה. Aliyah. Oh, when you get
an עליה, Aliyah, right, that's a good point as well. The right,
often ברכות, Berachos, multiple ברכות Berachos just reflect the fact that there's
multiple dimensions or that there's multiple things you want to talk about,
the מצוה, Mitzvah, the שבח Shevach and so on, but here again
it's אשר קדשנו, Asher Kidishanu, it's not a ברכת השבח, Birchas Hashevach,
so the grammar of that
part of the ברכה Beracha as well, אשר קדשנו על מצות תפילין,
Asher Kidishanu al mitzvas tefillin,
לשמור חקיו, Lishmor Chukav, לשמור חקיו?
Lishmor Chukav?
Oh, that's true. It's true. Whenever you get though to the to
the last part,
שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu,
שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו, Shehecheyanu vekiyemanu vehigianu, והיה, vehaya, בעצם עדיין, be'etzem adayin,
לעסוק
בדברי תורה La'asok bedivrei Torah and then והערב נא את דברי תורתך...
Veha'arev na es divrei Sorasecha... yeah, that's true, you do switch the
person. Okay, anyway, so let's move on. גופא, Gufa, thing גופא Gufa
note. Three lines down in the wide lines, אמר רבי אלעזר כל
המניח תפילין אחר שקיעת החמה עובר בעשה. Amar Rabbi Elazar kol hamaniach
tefillin achar shekias hachamah over be'aseh. And here you get the idea
where it's making... yes, yes it says ושמרת, okay. And here you
get the idea that it's not just you don't have the חיוב,
chiyuv if you base yourself on the פסוק pasuk you are not
allowed to do it into the night. רבי יוחנן ושמרת, Rabbi Yochanan
veshamarta, רבי יוחנן אמר עובר בלאו. Rabbi Yochanan amar over belav. So
אמר Amar ושמרת, שימור Shimur means a לא תעשה, Lo sa'aseh, like
שמור את יום השבת. Shmor es yom haShabbos. לימא בהא דרבי אבין
אמר רבי אילעא קמיפלגי, Lima be'ha deRabbi Abin amar Rabbi Ila kamifligi,
maybe they debate the debate of רבי אבין Rabbi Abin and רבי
אילעא, Rabbi Ila, דאמר רבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא כל מקום שנאמר
השמר פן ואל אינו אלא בלא תעשה. De'amar Rabbi Abin amar Rabbi
Ila kol makom shene'emar hishamer pen ve'al eino ela belo sa'aseh. When
the Torah says watch yourself lest and don't, it means it's a
negative prohibition. So therefore the question is, when it says ושמרת by
the, which we're saying means by the תפילין, Tefillin
does it mean a מצות עשה Mitzvas aseh or a לא תעשה?
Lo sa'aseh? מר אית ליה דרבי אבין, Mar is lei deRabbi Abin,
one holds like him and therefore it's a לא תעשה, Lo sa'aseh,
ומר לית ליה דרבי אבין, Umar leis lei deRabbi Abin, the other
doesn't hold like him. והגמרא אומרת לא, Vehagemara omeres lo, no. כולי
עלמא אית להו דרבי אבין, Kulei alma is lehu deRabbi Abin, everybody
holds like רבי אבין. Rabbi Abin. אמר רבי אילעא... Amar Rabbi Ila...
והכא בהא קמיפלגי. Ve'hacha be'ha kamifligi. מר סבר השמר דלאו לאו, Mar
savar hishamer delav lav, it's the השמר Hishamer when when the השמר
Hishamer goes on the Torah saying don't do this, watch yourself that
you shall not do the following, then watch that you shall not
means don't do it, a לא תעשה. Lo sa'aseh. השמר דעשה עשה,
Hishamer de'aseh aseh, watch yourself that you should do this, right, ושמרת
את החקה הזאת, Veshamarta es hachuka hazos, guard yourself that you should
do this, that's an עשה, that's a positive מצוה. Mitzvah. ומר סבר
השמר דעשה נמי לאו. Umar savar hishamer de'aseh nami lav. No, when
the Torah uses the word השמר, Hishamer, guard yourself, it means watch
yourself not to transgress sort of like, you know, not living up
to your obligation. So therefore השמר Hishamer always means a לא תעשה
Lo sa'aseh even if it's telling you to do something. Okay, והא...
Veha... so that's clearly about etc. that you don't have to but
you're not allowed to. ואמר רבי אלעזר... Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar... ואמר רבי
אלעזר דאם לשמרם מותר. Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar de'im leshomram mutar. However, if
you're putting on תפילין Tefillin, to protect them, it's permissible, which means
let's say for example, or you're keeping them on, it's nightfall and
you're on the, you're on a journey, you're in the, you're in
the middle of the road, and you're afraid that if you take
them off either they'll fall or drop, you won't be able to,
you know, keep them... you'll only protect them well if they're on
your body. And it's already nightfall, so then you can keep them
on.
Keep it on החזקה Hachazaka of nightfall if you're worried about it
then it's fine? Presumably, yes.
רש"י Rashi says מותר להניחן אפילו אחר שקיעת החמה, Mutar lehannichan afilu
achar shekias hachama, it's even permissible to put them on. The גמרא
Gemara had classic examples by the way about שבת, that there's a
fire or whatever, you see תפילין, Tefillin. you know, in the street
and it's שבת and you don't have an עירוב, Eiruv, and שבת
is לאו זמן תפילין, Tefillin. are you allowed to wear the תפילין
to bring them to safety? So א, Alef, the question is, שבת
לאו זמן תפילין, Shabbos lav zman tefillin, is it carrying? Was it
wearing? And then, you know, also the שבת לאו זמן תפילין. Shabbos
lav zman tefillin. But on those special circumstances it's not seen as
somehow compromising because presumably then they're not being worn as an אות,
right? If they're not being worn as an אות, it doesn't raise
the issue.
Okay, as the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, ואמר רבינא. Ve'amar Ravina. So רבינא Ravina said הוינא יתיבנא קמיה
דרב אשי, Havina yasivna kamei deRav Ashi, I was sitting in front
of רב אשי, Rav Ashi, וחשך ואניח תפילין, Vechashach ve'annich tefillin, and
it grew dark and he put on תפילין. Because although it was
already dark and he put them on, he didn't just leave them
on. This is pretty surprising because before we had set down the
line that even if you held
that
לילה לאו זמן תפילין... meaning for whatever reason, I'm going to take
them home and I'm afraid something will happen, so that's why I'm
putting them on. Okay,
and so, excuse me, ואמרי ליה, v'amrei lei, actually, let me reread
that, ואמרי ליה, v'amrei lei, we said to him: לשמור קא בעי
להו מר? lishmor ka bei lehu mar? You need it in—are you
doing this because you need to protect them? ואמר לי, v'amar li,
and he said to me: אין, in, yes, that's why I'm doing
it. וחזיתיה בדעתיה, vachaziteih bedateih, but I could tell his intention, דלאו
לשמור בעי, delav lishmor bei, that he really was not doing it
to protect them. So why were we going through this whole little
ruse?
קסבר, he held: הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. The
real הלכה halacha is, is that לילה is זמן תפילין. He had
nothing to do with שמירה. shmira. He indeed held לילה was זמן
תפילין, but he didn't—he felt you were not allowed to publicize this
הלכה. halacha. הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. Because presumably,
because people would, you know, maybe it would lead to people falling
asleep with them, drifting off from the whole thing, so even though
מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin you can leave them on until it gets
much later... and
well, okay. The question is putting. The צידה לדרך Tzeidah LaDerech switches
the גרסה. girsa. Take a look at the little ב. He switches
the גרסה girsa that he left them on. Putting them on goes
against things we were saying before. דחשך והוי מנח תפילין ולא סליק
תפילין. dechashach vehavei manach tefillin velo salik tefillin. He was wearing his
תפילין and he didn't take them off. So he tries to make
this conform to the earlier גמרא Gemara that says that everybody agrees
you don't put them on, you just don't have to take them
off. Regardless, anyway, he felt that this is an עיקר הלכה. ikar
halacha. Yes, you are allowed, but because it's about protecting your body
and being aware and so on, we don't want to go ahead
and publicize this הלכה. halacha. הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin
kein. Which raises interesting questions with the הלכה ואין מורין כן halacha
v'ein morin kein about, are you allowed to actually say the הלכה
halacha is something else? Or you don't say what the הלכה halacha
is? Or do you, you know, do you sort of obfuscate a
little bit like, you know, so, and גרס Gers wouldn't even tell
his תלמיד talmid that.
There's a very famous גמרא Gemara in
ביצה. Beitzah. I think it's ביצה Beitzah where the question is—there's a
whole question about are you allowed to do on
יום טוב like מכשירי אוכל נפש? machshirei ochel nefesh? And there's a
whole question
about...
so the גמרא Gemara raises a question about turning off a light
for a couple, you know, who basically want on יום טוב, who
want to be together in private and the table to be—to have
sex. Are you allowed to do that or not? So for whatever
reason the גמרא Gemara sees that this is tied into the question
about מכשירי אוכל נפש. machshirei ochel nefesh. This may be one step
removed, whatever the case might be. Anyway, so they ask the rabbi
and they said—whoever, I forget who it was, they asked the אמורא
Amora and they said: Are you allowed to do it? And he
said: Well, why don't you build a wall? Well, you know, like
put up—well, what you can't, well, why don't you go to another
room? Well, why don't you do this? Why don't you do that?
And they kept it up and he said: פיי, fei, טיפשא. tipsha.
And then the גמרא Gemara says... so a number of ראשונים Rishonim
say—the גמרא Gemara doesn't say it, a number of ראשונים say he
really held הלכה ואין מורין כן, halacha v'ein morin kein, so he
didn't want to tell him it was אסור, but he wasn't taking
a hint. So finally, but you know it raises interesting questions about
הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. What does that mean?
How do you, you know, how do you sort of like not
say—not misrepresent הלכה, halacha, but at the same time, you know, it's
the גמרא's Gemara attitude. I'm not sure anybody has an attitude nowadays,
you know, that, you know, sort of like the what's-his-name from that
movie, Jack Nicholson, that movie, where was it? You can't handle the
truth. Now, so what was that movie? Remember that? The truth, you
can't—so, you know, it's the גמרא's Gemara idea. What? A Few Good
Men. So anyway, you know, the גמרא's Gemara idea about
whether—and there is a reality about that. You know, you tell people
a certain הלכה, halacha, in certain cases, you know, you tell them...
בדיעבד bedieved becomes לכתחילה, lechatchila, you know, and how much do we—or
how much do the rabbis control sometimes the flow of information if
they think that it will lead to people flipping and sliding? That's
an interesting category of הלכה ואין מורין כן, halacha v'ein morin kein,
yeah.
But did anyone have the צידה לדרך Tzeidah LaDerech actually switches the
גרסה girsa on me? Yeah. They'll look and for sure say that
really he held לכתחילה דרבנן lechatchila derabbanan תפילין at night and—not just
בדיעבד. bedieved.
I don't know, I'd have to check, because everything I've gone by...
I mean, it's only because like, you know, right. I'd rather not
have to change a גרסה. girsa. I understand, so.
Okay, let's take a look. אמר רבה בר רב הונא: חייב אדם
למשמש בתפילין Chayav adam lemashmesh bitefillin בכל שעה. bechol sha'ah. And I
mentioned it a minute ago. A person has to constantly be like
touching תפילין at every moment. קל וחומר מציץ. Kal vachomer m'tzitz. ומה
ציץ שאין בו
אלא אזכרה אחת, U'mah tzitz she'ein bo ela azkarah achas, אמרה תורה
והיה על מצחו תמיד. amrah Torah vehayah al mitzcho tamid. So the
ציץ only has one mention of G-d's name, קודש לה'. Kodesh l'Hashem.
It says constantly on his forehead. Of course, it doesn't mean he's
touching it. All right, but whatever. So but from the word תמיד
tamid we learn, or from the word והיה, I'm not sure, anyway
תמיד tamid we learn שלא תסיח דעתו הימנו. shelo tasiach dato heimenu.
Rabbinically we interpret this to mean he cannot let his awareness stray.
תפילין שיש בהן אזכרות הרבה, Tefillin sheyesh bahen azkaros harbei, תפילין has
many mentions of G-d's names, על אחת כמה וכמה. al achas kamah
v'chamah. How much more so shall you constantly keep your awareness הימנו.
heimenu. ומסיח U'masiach means on your arm?
I understand, so you're right. So למשמש lemashmesh is not really למשמש.
lemashmesh. It means to remain conscious of its presence, not to just...
and that can happen, you know, you're wearing something. It's
a technique. Exactly, it's not
technically required to
למשמש. lemashmesh. So... The purpose of having the שם השם shem Hashem
on you is to be conscious of God. So you have to,
in order to achieve the purpose here, how it, so you have
to, you have to constantly be aware that you're wearing this to
maintain that God-consciousness, and I think that fits in very much with
the גמרא Gemara about the אות and why the אות by
שבת therefore obviates the need. And like I said, the ציצית Tzitzit.
you have, you don't wear the ציצית tzitzit. when you go into
the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodoshim. I think it's a way of sort
of seeing how the two are functioning in similar ways. Okay, so
let's take a look.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now the גמרא Gemara brings specifically הלכות halachos
about how you wear it.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: ידך זו שמאל. Yadcha zu smol. ידך is
your left. אתה אומר שמאל או אינו אלא ימין? Atah omer smol
o eino ela yamin? You say left, perhaps it's only the right?
תלמוד לומר. Talmud lomar: And who knows what יד yad means? Who
knows what hand means?
תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar אף
ידי יסדה ארץ וימיני טפחה שמים. Af yadi yasdah eretz viymini tipchah
shamayim. My hand has sort of founded the earth and my right
hand has, you know, sort of molded the heavens. So יד yad
as opposed to ימין, yamin, the ימין yamin is the right, so
the יד yad would be the left. ואומר, Veomer, and the פסוק
pasuk
says:
ידה ליתד תשלחנה וימינה
להלמות
עמלים. Yadah layased tishlachnah viyminah lehalmus amelim. So this is by יעל,
Yael, right, killing סיסרא. Sisra. Her hand she stretched out to the
pent, to the tent peg, and her right hand to the הלמות
עמלים, halmus amelim, as I assume it's a hand hammer or something.
So therefore, if you got your hammer in your right hand and
your יד yad is holding the tent peg, your יד yad is
your left hand. ואומר, Veomer, that's I think that's probably the better
proof than the God, because יד yad and ימין yamin might just
be, you know, synonyms. But here you're hammering, you need two hands.
What?
Maybe he has three hands. God?
Okay, אוי. oy. Heresy, heresy! ואומר: Veomer: למה תשיב ידך וימינך מקרב
חיקך כלה? Lamah tashiv yadcha viyminecha mikerev cheikecha kaleh? Why will you
hold back your hand and your right hand from your, from your,
from you know, from your bosom? Why? There could just be parallels,
there could be synonyms, it's not two different things. Anyway, the גמרא
is understanding that יד yad means left because ימין yamin means ימין.
yamin. Anyway, כלה, kaleh, with which we all done.
So רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi now the top of לז עמוד א,
lamed zayin amud aleph,
רבי יוסי החורם אומר. Rabbi Yossi Hachorem omer. So רבי יוסי החורם.
Rabbi Yossi Hachorem. What does החורם Hachorem mean? So if you look
at רש"י, Rashi, צבאתי? tzva'ati? No, חוטמו משוקע, chotmo meshuka, he had
like a sort of I don't know what's it called, a pressed-in
nose. המאמין בבכורות חרום זה שחוטמו משוקע. Hamamin bevochoros charum zeh shechotmo
meshuka. The גמרא that says that, בכורות Bechoros דף מג. daf mem
gimmel. תוספות Tosafot says, look at תוספות: Tosafot, פירש בקונטרס חוטמו היה
שקוע כעין חרום דבבכורות. Peirash bakontres chotmo hayah shaku'a k'ein charum debechoros.
ותימה לומר שהזכירו בלשון גנאי. Veseimah lomar shehizkiro bilshon gnay. Why would
they just call him, you know, old bent nose, the bent-nose רבי
יוסי or something? דהלא על שם מקומו נקרא כן. Dehalo al shem
mekomo nikra kein. Alright, that was where his location, that was where
he was, חורם Chorem was the name of a place. So I
appreciate תוספות's Tosafot, sensitivity to not assume we're dealing with nicknames. What?
דוב? Dov?
I hate to be the grammar, you know, picking up the grammar
here. דהחורם Dehachorem would be somebody who makes other people's nose?
That is a good point.
Actually if you look at the שיטה מקובצת, Shitah Mekubetzet, רבי יוסי
החרום. Rabbi Yossi Hacharum. רבי יוסי החרום. Rabbi Yossi Hacharum. He has
it. Okay,
there you go.
Okay, back to the גמרא. רבי יוסי החורם אומר, Rabbi Yossi Hachorem
omer, החרום אומר: Hacharum omer: מצינו ימין שנקרא יד. Matzinu yamin shenikra
yad. Don't tell me יד yad means left. יד yad can mean
right. שנאמר: Shene'emar: וירא יוסף כי ישית אביו יד ימינו. Vayar Yosef
ki yashis aviv yad yemino. No, it doesn't, that's not the proof,
so the גמרא says like מאי כהאי? mai kehai? The response would
be יד ימינו איקרי. Yad yemino ikrei. If you have a modifier,
his right hand, then fine, then יד yad can mean right. יד
סתמא, Yad stama, both without a modifier, the word יד yad by
itself, לא איקרי, lo ikrei, it would not be called the right
hand, it would refer to the left. רבי נתן אומר אינו צריך,
Rabbi Natan omer eino tzarich, you do not need it.
הרי הוא אומר: Harei hu omer: וקשרתם וכתבתם, Ukeshartem uchtavtem, that you
shall bind and you shall write. מה כתיבה בימין, Mah ktivah beyamin,
the same way writing is with your right hand, most people are
righties, אף קשירה בימין, af kshirah beyamin, the binding is in the
right hand. So if you're going to bind with your right,
וכיון דקשירה בימין, vekeivan dekshirah beyamin, הנחה בשמאל, hanachah bismol, it would
be placed on your left. I want to get back to that
just hold off, I'm going to get back to that in a
minute, but now we're basing it based on its connection to כתיבה,
ktivah, which is very different from just an arbitrary
identifying in the פסוק.
pasuk What if you're lefty, you have to put it on...
right, so the גמרא is going to deal with that. So let's
take a look. ורבי יוסי החורם VeRabbi Yossi Hachorem or החרום, Hacharum,
הנחה דבשמאל מנא ליה? hanachah devismol m'na lei? Since he says יד
yad can mean right, how do you know you put your תפילין
on your left hand? נפקא ליה מהיכא דנפקא ליה לרבי נתן, Nafka
lei meheicha denafka lei leRabbi Natan, from where רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
gets it, וקשרתם וכתבתם, Ukeshartem uchtavtem, a different פסוק. Okay, רב אשי
אמר מידכה, Rav Ashi amar miyadchah, we get it from the פסוק
of ידכה, yadchah, which is written כף ה. kaf hei. כתיב בה,
Kativ beheh, it's written with a ה, hei, not just a כף
סופית. kaf sofit. So we read כה kah as if it says
יד כה, yad keh, your weak arm. יד כהה. Yad kehah. Okay,
so that's how we know your left.
אמר ליה רבא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rava leRav Ashi, ואימא ידך
שבכח, ve'eima yadcha shebechoach, maybe the כף ה kaf hei is a
כח koach essentially, you know, for the ה hei almost looks like
a חית? ches? So maybe your strong arm? אמר ליה מי כתיב
בחית? Amar lei mi kativ b'ches? It's not written with a חית,
ches, it's written with a ה. hei. Okay, תניא אידך, Tanya idach,
תניא אידך, tanya idach, yes, there is this
exchange. ידכה בה Yadecha be-he with ה, he, זו שמאל, zu smol,
your left hand. אחרים אומרים ידכה Acheirim omrim yadecha לרבות את הגידם.
le-rabos et ha-gidam. So the reason it says ידכה yadecha maybe also
with, again, they switch it to the כה kaf he weak arm,
it's to tell you even a person who has amputated arm would
still put on תפילין. Now the question is where? So the presumption
is that not the entire arm is amputated, maybe it's only from
the elbow down, or maybe it's but presumably there is enough left
of the muscle that you would put it, you could put it
where you would normally put your תפילין, but you don't have the
whole hand. So maybe I'm thinking, it's not just where you put
your תפילין, you need a hand, you need a whole hand there.
No, ידכה yadecha weak tells you even if a person is amputated
you can still put on תפילין if there's still a מקום. makom.
So then it wouldn't be יד, yad, it would be, you know,
זרועך zeroacha or something.
Well, that's, yeah, well that's, I guess, well that's a general problem.
How do you know יד yad means here and not on your
palm? We'll look at that in a minute.
Okay, so רבנו Rabbenu and all that stuff where it was simply
the right
hand.
The פסוקים pesukim says, אצבע, etzba, אצבע מן כהן. etzba min Kohen.
Yeah, right, not from יד. yad. That's a good point, not from
יד, yad, right, right, it wasn't יד, yad, it was אצבע, etzba,
אצבע מן כהן etzba min Kohen were ימין, yamin, right, but not
יד. yad. Yeah. So the גמרא says like this:
Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, now we're going to talk about this
גידם. gidam. תניא אידך, tanya idach, אין לו זרוע פטור מן התפילין.
ein lo zeroa patur min ha-tefillin. If you do not have an
arm, you are exempt from תפילין.
How are they defining it as what? A whole arm or?
Again, let's assume it means, I'll talk a little bit more about
it in a minute, let's assume it means, you know, right, at
least from your elbow down. That's the זרוע? zeroa? Yeah. Well, then,
no,
that's normally actually referred to as the קיבה. keivah. The זרוע zeroa
is normally referred to as the place up here. So I'm going
to, let me bracket that for a minute because you're thinking like,
I understand, I have what to say about this, so hold on
a minute. Okay. פטור מן התפילין. patur min ha-tefillin. אחרים אומרים ידכה,
Acheirim omrim yadecha, no, we say לרבות את הגידם le-rabos et ha-gidam
that even amputated is חייב. chayav, Let's just read one more about
this יד yad and then I'll talk about all these issues that
we just raised. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, איטר, iter, if somebody is
a lefty, learned from a פסוק in תנ"ך Tanach where it says
that a person was איטר יד ימינו, iter yad yemino, oh, his
right hand was bound. Right, hand bound figuratively. So what it means
like he was a lefty, נבך, nebach, he couldn't use his right
hand. Okay, that would be me. איטר, iter, right, exactly, that's me,
all my family, myself, my wife and two kids, all lefties.
You're lucky. Okay.
איטר מניח תפילין בימינו,
iter
maniach
tefillin bi-yemino, his right hand, meaning his strong hand, his... I'm sorry,
I again I'm getting mixed up. Let me just check רש"י Rashi
again, it gets confusing, one minute. Okay, הוא שמאלו, hu smolo, but
which does he mean? רש"י Rashi says, right, ימין של איטר הוא
שמאל לדידיה, yamin shel iter hu smol le-didei, right, meaning his literal
right hand, which is what you know I do, on what we
would call my right hand, שהיא שמאלו she-hi smolo which is his
weak hand, meaning שמאל smol the second
it's named figuratively. So in order to get weak hand, you would
put it on for you who your weak hand is, which would
be your right hand. והתניא מניח בשמאלו שהיא שמאל כל אדם? Ve-hatanya
maniach bi-smolo she-hi smol kol adam? Oh, don't we have a ברייתא
Baraita. that says even a lefty puts it on his left hand?
So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, כי תניא היא בשלטי בשתי ידיו. ki
tanya hi bi-shalti bi-shtei yadav. When we're talking about somebody who is
ambidextrous, then, okay, if it's ambidextrous you go by the norm, which
is most people are righties, so you put it on the left
hand. Do we have a lot of interesting things here about the
hands? Let me talk about and the גידם, gidam, whatever, let me
talk about a few of them. First is the issue I would
say the simple sense of the ברייתא braita: which אביי Abaye rejects,
which is do you say it's objectively left or do you say
it's weak? And the נפקא מינה nafka mina is the lefty. To
the degree that could be learned out from the פסוקים, pesukim, right?
If the פסוקים pesukim understand that יד yad just means שמאל, smol,
then I don't care if you're a righty or a lefty, everybody
puts it on their left. If it somehow means weak hand, יד
כהה, yad kehah, וקשרתם וכתבתם, ukshartam u-chtavtam, then it's going to be
different for a lefty, which is how we פסקן pasken and how
אביי Abaye reads to reconcile these two ברייתות. braitos. The question then
becomes what happens, oh, so that's one thing. Now the question about
the emphasis of וקשרתם, ukshartam, what does that tell you?
So in my mind that's significant because it is again bringing in
this question about whether תפילין is wearing or binding, is it like
a state or is it this action? And saying וקשרתם וכתבתם ukshartam
u-chtavtam maybe he shifts. We normally think of the הלכה halacha is
תפילין goes on your weak hand. But what if I said it
differently? What if I said the הלכה halacha is you have to
bind your תפילין with your right hand? Right? It makes us think
about it very differently. You say, the fact that you put it
on your left is incidental. The real point is there's a מעשה
מצוה maaseh mitzvah of binding, and the same way there's a מעשה
מצוה maaseh mitzvah of writing, you know, וכתבתם, u-chtavtam, and the מעשה
מצוה maaseh mitzvah is done with your right hand, at least for
most people. So therefore to do וקשרתם, ukshartam, קשרתם kshartam requires ימין.
yamin. That's not normally how we articulate it, but it makes us
think very differently about it, and I think that that's one of
the questions about תפילין. How much is the emphasis on the act
of וקשרתם, ukshartam how much is the emphasis on the wearing of
it? Now an important נפקא מינה nafka mina about this about how
much you emphasize יד כהה yad kehah versus וקשרתם Ukeshartam is the
question that תוספות Tosafot raises, which comes up all the time. Well
ambidextrous we already said, but more than that, look at תוספות, Tosafot
מה כתיבה בימין אף קשירה בימין. mah ketivah be-yamin af kshirah be-yamin.
So says תוספות, בסמוך אמרינן דאיטר מניח תפילין בימינו שהיא שמאלו. be-samuch
amrinan de-iter maniach tefillin bi-yemino she-hi smolo. That a lefty puts it
on his right hand. So the גמרא says, והא סתם אדם הכותב
בימינו ושאר רוב מעשיו בשמאלו, ve-ha stam adam ha-kotev bi-yemino ve-shaar rov
maasav bi-smolo, somebody that basically... basically is a lefty but writes with
his right hand. You could also imagine the opposite. יש להסתפק דאיזה
מהן מניח תפילין. Yeish l'histapeik d'eizeh meihen maniyach tefillin. Which one? So
basically, you know, you can just make it a technical question: if
you emphasize וקשרתם וכתבתם, Ukeshartam Ukhtavtam, it's all a question of which
hand you write with. If you emphasize יד כהה, yad keiha, so
maybe, you know, you go by your generally your weak arm regardless
of which one is writing with. ושמא יש לדמותו כשותף שתי ידיו.
V'shema yeish l'dimoto k'shotaf shtei yadav. So תוספות says, which is a
good point, like well maybe it will play look hey, on the
one hand you have your strength of writing and on the other
hand you have your other, you know, you have the כהה, keiha,
so well we'll sort of when in doubt tip in favor of
going like most people, tip in favor of treating yourself like a
righty and putting it on your left hand. On the other thing
of course you could say about that is another reason to treat
that person as if they're right-handed is they could say look, on
the one hand if you base yourself on the דרשה drasha וקשרתם,
Ukeshartam, it's going to be clearly we're going to treat you as
right-handed.
And even if you base yourself on
one minute, and even if you base yourself on the פסוק of
יד כהה, yad keiha,
you know, weak hand, it's it's debatable which is your weak hand
here. On the one hand you do a lot of things with
your with your left, on the other hand you write with your
right hand. That's a pretty important thing, which you write with. So
the יד כהה yad keiha is already debatable and וקשרתם Ukeshartam clearly
tips in favor of treating you as a righty. Those cases are
easier, somebody therefore to treat that person basically as a righty to
put on your left hand. It's more complicated when you have a
flip when somebody writes with their left and does I don't know
if that happened too often, I don't know as matter of logically
I guess should write with her left and does other things with
their right, because then you say if you go by וקשרתם Ukeshartam
you're going to treat this person as lefty. If you go by
יד כהה yad keiha then you'll say it's evenly based or maybe
we'll treat them as a righty. So they're tipping more in favor
of the lefty. How do you deal with that? So I think
as I said that part of this is, so there's a real
נפקא מינה nafka mina by these cases, and part of it is
how much we emphasize is it where it is placed or is
how you are binding it. And I think you know the conceptual
question of how much is it a מצוה mitzvah of וקשרתם Ukeshartam
and what we're saying is קשירה בימין, keshira b'yamin, or how much
is it a מצוה mitzvah of wearing תפילין and we have to
figure out which body part you wear it on and we say
the weak hand. What did you want to add?
No, I guess what I'm saying is I just don't understand this.
וקשרתם ukeshartem וכתבתם, Ukhtavtam, but I mean, so why is it just
the hand you write with? Also the hand you do קשירה, keshira,
which to me would mean like, you know, it's just because you
write with the right hand big deal, but you have to do
the קשירה keshira also. To me seems like just as important
and that would be from a juxtaposition. You're right, the word קשירה
keshira by itself does not mean קשירה בימין, keshira b'yamin, but juxtaposed
with וכתבתם ukhtavtam it means...
but you could say the opposite, קשירה כתיבה, keshira ktiva, just like
you write if you be right to left hand and, you know,
you know what I'm saying? No, why is it going that way?
That the hand you would be writing with is the hand...
No, the only
question to ask, no, that's not a...
no, people do not have a designated hand for tying. People have
a designated hand for writing. So, you know, the only question that
you... so I you know, I don't think that is a question.
Really? I mean, I'm thinking from my perspective because I'm such an
extreme lefty I can't even... okay... keep it out of the world,
I
mean other than תפילין for tying you usually use both hands.
Right, you got one to hold, you whatever. Anyway, the גמרא I
think is seeing that people... the גמרא is assuming that handedness is
much more about writing than it is about something like קשירה. keshira.
That's probably because it is, for other for you, for a lot
of people that's the way it is. Okay.
For generations of people who
were forced to become right-handed. Right. And then they create interesting הלכה
halacha questions about,
you know, they write with their right hand but probably their left
hand
is really their dominant hand. Yeah, there's a lot of interesting הלכה
halacha literature about exactly this. How do we פסקן pasken that תוספות's
question and which דרשה drasha you see is primary in your type
of cases where somebody really was forced essentially, really became an איטר,
iter, not an איטר יד ימינו, iter yad yemino, an איטר יד
שמאלו, iter yad smolo, that happened in Europe often. Anyway, these always
interesting questions and a case and interesting for me conceptual question of
an act of קשירה keshira or do we say an act of
wearing. Now the other thing is I want to talk about the
גידם. gidem. First of all in terms of הלכה, halacha, so of
course Michael comes like oh well there's a debate and it's a
מחלוקת in a ברייתא. How do we rule?
Okay,
actually not exactly clear. It's a reasonable question.
It's a reasonable question. Actually there's a question how we rule because
it says like this, it says...
no, what is a גידם? gidem?
Right, well both of these are related. So in סימן כז, siman
chaf-zayin, the...
it's not in the מחבר, Mechaber, it's in the רמ״א. Rema. גידם
Gidem שאין לו יד רק זרוע. she'ein lo yad rak zeroa. So
notice שאין לו יד רק זרוע, she'ein lo yad rak zeroa, so
he does have the זרוע, zeroa, okay, יניח בלא ברכה. yaniach belo
bracha. So that's how he splits it. It's a debate of דאורייתא,
d'Oraita, so we say put it on without a ברכה, bracha, but
you do have the זרוע. zeroa. והמשנה ברורה V'HaMishna Berura
says, ואם אין לו יד שמאל כלל, v'im ein lo yad smol
klal, then he says if you don't have the place to be
מניח תפילין, maniyach tefillin, you don't have the part of the muscle
of the upper arm where you מניח תפילין, maniyach tefillin, of course
everybody says there's no point in putting it on the stump that's
not... put it in another hand? No, so you don't wear it.
You don't wear it.
Okay. וכל זה אבל שנחתך גידם דהוא ימין מקום הנחה אבל נחתך
גידם בימין, V'chol zeh aval shenichtach gidem d'hu yemin mekom hanacha aval
neichtach gidem b'yamin, he says if however a person does not have
their right arm, then get somebody else to put תפילין on for
you. Okay, you still have a מצוה, mitzvah, you can't actually do
the binding, have somebody else do it. And that actually has to,
you know, happens, you know,
I knew a case when I was growing up with a kid
that had some type of a paralysis or whatever and anyway he
could not bind his own תפילין and somebody else had to. come
and bind his תפילין for him. That by the way, not to
take it from the very profound personal thing and to make it
a immediate edge or whatever, emotion,
but anyway make it a immediate shift into הלכתי halakhic categories, but
I think it's also interesting in terms of how to be analytical
about it and interesting in terms of our question about whether it's
מצוה mitzvah to wear or מצוה mitzvah to bind. Because if a
person doesn't have their right arm, then they're an אונס, annus, they
can't be commanded to bind, they don't have they can't bind, they
don't have their right arm. And nevertheless, we assume that no, of
course they're commanded to wear תפילין and somebody just has to get
it on them. So of course we assume that, you know, that
there is this aspect of wearing. The question still is which is
primary and conceptually and so on. But anyway, if you take a
look Michael in the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah in the ביאור הלכה
Biur Halakha there, he has a whole discussion about which part of
the arm and maybe the ראשונים all really agree that as long
as the upper arm is there you are חייב, you know, and
maybe the whole debate was they were simply if you take a
look there he has it. But generally
the simple פסק psak is is that if he is that there
might be a possibility if the whole arm isn't there, even if
the upper arm is, that maybe the person is פטור patur and
the הלכה halakha is you put it on a person, such a
person would put it on without a ברכה. brakha.
Wait, so if you're missing if you're missing the arm entirely, if
you're missing your weak arm entirely and you don't put on תפילין
at all and no one says
that you don't put on של יד, shel yad, you put on
your של ראש. shel rosh. Okay and you make both ברכות brakhos
on the של ראש. shel rosh. Okay, right? Because that goes to
our point yesterday that the של ראש shel rosh requires two ברכות
brakhos but you're יוצא yotze with one with the של יד.
shel yad. No, no you would say you just put it on
your, you know, your strong have someone else put it on your
strong hand.
Right, but that's the whole מצוה. mitzvah. That again points to our
general orientation, emphasizes not the קשירה kshira but the wearing. And therefore
that we basically assume wear on your left, that's the body part
that you wear תפילין, if you don't have that body person doesn't
have their body part, you're an אונס, annus, no place to wear
the של יד. shel yad.
You would still wear the של ראש shel rosh with both ברכות.
brakhos.
I'll say with two ברכות. brakhos. בזמן פטורים, bizman paturim, right.
Now, I wanted to show you quickly, of course, not like we're
not behind already, but I just had to show you this a
רב משה Rav Moshe here, one of the first רב משה'ס Rav
Moshes in אורח חיים, Orach Chayim, he's asked about somebody who was
paralyzed, has paralysis in his arm, some part of whatever, and is
this person, is it like he does not have that arm? So
we already talked like, you know, maybe you need somebody to help
you put on the תפילין, would it be like that that person
would not have an arm? Would he be allowed to wear תפילין,
you know, with a ברכה? brakha? So רב משה Rav Moshe says
if the arm is totally, he has paralysis in the arm. Which
one? The left arm, the weak arm. Okay, so so if if
it's like the arm isn't there, or a ספק whatever, you wouldn't
make a ברכה. brakha. If it's like the arm is there, it
just can't move it, then you don't make then you do make
a ברכה. brakha. Okay, so רב משה Rav Moshe has a whole
discussion about what happens if the hand is really shriveled and no
longer has blood running through it and there he says that even
if it's physically connected, it's not considered an arm and then you
would not, you know, you you would not make a ברכה brakha
to really went up to the מקום הנחת תפילין. makom hanachas tefillin.
If it was a lower part, you know, you would do it
as ספק. But if it's shriveled and it's without blood, even if
it's physically present, then it's not an arm. But what about paralysis?
So here he says, it's the one that says on the right-hand
column has סימן ט' siman tet on the bottom אורח חיים Orach
Chayim it says on the top. Okay, it's the first right-hand column
the second paragraph, he said אבל במחלת הפאראליזיס aval b'machalat haparalysis
הפאראליז haparaliz
ברור שמותי דם הרבה, barur shemoti dam harbeh, right? So he's obviously
got blood flowing, the arm is healthy in terms of that כמו
ביד בריא k'mo b'yad bari לכן אין צריך לחזקה כלל ליבש שעשו
כחסר lachayn ein tzarich l'chazaka klal l'yavesh she'asu k'chasayr like something dried
that's considered not there. הברור שיצא, habarur sheyatza, I'll skip his dot
dot dot. Then he says וגם, v'gam, I'm like about five lines
in after the period, אין ניכר בו שום יבש כלל ein nikar
bo shum yavesh klal רק שמחלה כזו שאינו מרגיש בו היד ואינו
יכול להניע, rak shemachala k'zu she'eino margish bo hayad v'eino yachol l'hani'ah,
you can't move it, וברוב הפעמים אין הסיבה כלל ביד, u'b'rov hapa'amim
ein hasiba klal b'hayad, it's not prominent in the arm, אלא מצד
מחלה שבמוח, ela mitzad machala shebamoch, it's in the, you know, it's
in the brain or the spinal cord or the nerves, לכן אף
שאינו יכול להשתמש בו לא הוי כחסר lachayn af she'eino yachol l'hishtamesh
bo lo havay k'chasayr וממילא מחויב בתפילין להניח לו על כל
יד שמאלי u'mimayla mechuyav b'tefillin l'haniach lo al kol yad smoli with
a ברכה. brakha. Okay, with a ברכה. brakha. Okay, וגם v'gam and
now this is interesting אולי ידוע כלפי שמיא שיש לזה רפואה ulay
yadua klapei shamaya sheyesh l'ze refuah אף שרופאים שלנו אינם יודעים מה
הרפואה, af she'rofim shelanu einam yodim ma harefuah, which is why that
should better. Anyway, על כל פנים al kol panim אין להחשיב כחסר
ein l'hachshiv k'chasayr אלא מה שמצינו שהוא
בשיעור השד שניקב ela matzanu shehu b'shi'ur hashochen yakave etc etc. And
then he says like this, oh and then this was very very
touching at the end, זכורני, z'chorni, four lines before the paragraph is
over, שאבא מרי הגאון זצ"ל, she'abba mari hagaon zatzal, my father, שהיה
לו עלינו חולה שבעה
חודשים האחרונים shehaya lo alaynu choleh shiva chodashim ha'acharonim his seven last
months of life מחמת מחלת הפאראליזיס, machamat machalas haparalysis, he was paralyzed
his last seven months of life מצדו השמאלי, m'tzido hasmoli, his left
side of his body, הניח תפילין על ידו השמאלי אף שגם כאן
פאראליזיסריטה hiniach tefillin al yado hasmoli af shegam kahn paralysis-rita whatever anyway
he put on תפילין okay on his left paralyzed arm. Okay so
he says that therefore you should put it on, you make a
ברכה brakha and the whole thing.
It feels like יד כהה, yad kehah, this is like the extreme.
That's a good point, this is a real כהה, kehah, right? But
as the גמרא says כהה kehah yes, but it still has to
be there. So is this considered there, you know, if you can't
control it? Okay, so that okay, so that's that. The other side
by the way which I won't read inside is רב משה Rav
Moshe again from יורה דעה Yoreh Deah ב' קמ"ו beis kuf mem
vav where he talks about the idea that the גמרא says you
use the diagonal to... Figure out the תפילין *tefillin*, that the fact
that the diagonal is not exactly 1.4 but it's 1.41, he says
that is the גמרא *Gemara* telling you what an acceptable round accuracy
error is, tolerance of, you know, and some and there, you know,
and why in other areas of הלכה Halacha. *halacha* do we need
to use microscopes,
do we need to, you know, clarify things, how precise we
have to be, so he uses this example about the diagonal of
תפילין *tefillin*. Very interesting. It's like the top of the second column.
Okay, let's go on. So back to the גמרא *Gemara*. The גמרא
*Gemara* says like this.
Wait, we didn't still understand how we know that it means your
arm, not your hand, right?
That's what we're about to say. Good, you're a good segue person.
Okay. אמר תנא דבי מנשה *Amar Tanna d'vei Menashe*, we talked about
אמר תנא דבי מנשה *Amar Tanna d'vei Menashe*. על ידך *Al yadecha*,
your hand, זו קיבורת *zu kibores*, this is your muscle. בין עיניך
Bein einecha *Bein einecha*, your between your eyes, זו קדקד *zu kadkod*,
this is like your what do you call this part of your?
Anyway, it's your skull, not your forehead, but your your cranium, your
skull, I don't know. Anyway, whatever, this part where you put your
תפילין *tefillin*. Okay. So היכא *heicha*? What? היכא
*heicha*? Is there a medical term for that? היכא
*Heicha*, אמר דבי רבי ינאי *amar
d'vei Rabbi Yannai*. Where exactly? אמר דבי רבי ינאי *Amar d'vei Rabbi
Yannai* says מקום שמוחו של תינוק רופס *Makom shemocho shel tinok ropes*.
The part where the soft spot on an infant's on a baby's
skull, right? What is it, like the two halves haven't solidified yet
or something? Higher up?
Really? Yeah?
It's like right here.
Really, it's not closer to the forehead? No. No. Now, do say
מקום יש בראש להניח שני תפילין *makom yesh barosh lehaniach shenei tefillin*.
We say it's where No, not here. Okay, so that, okay. So
we do say, and we're about to learn this, we're about to
learn this from the comparison to נגעים Negaim. *negaim*, that you put
the תפילין *tefillin* במקום שיער *bemakom se'ar*, where the hair grows, which
is for people that have like receding hair lines they say where
the hair used to grow from, okay? So it's start at the
roots of your hair. And the גמרא *Gemara* also says מקום יש
בראש להניח שני תפילין *makom yesh barosh lehaniach shenei tefillin*. And I'm
talking about small stone, they didn't have our sized תפילין *tefillin*, but
obviously it's not just here, you have a certain amount of height
above the bottom of the hairline that you know so a certain
amount of length. So I think if you go like just from
the hairline probably up about two inches, you're probably in that spot
of the מקום *makom*. Although we do tend to wear it so
that the bottom of the תפילין *tefillin* is right at the bottom
of the hair of where the hair comes out from. Okay. So
בעי מיניה פלימו מרבי *Ba'ei minei Plimo me'Rabbi*, פלימו *Plimo* asked from
רבי *Rabbi*. מי שיש לו שני ראשים *Mi sheyesh lo shenei rashim*,
if
somebody had two heads, באיזה מהן מניח תפילין *be'eizeh mehen maniach tefillin*?
Which one does he put תפילין *tefillin* on? So רבי *Rabbi*, אמר
ליה Amar leih, *amar lei*, so רבי *Rabbi* said to him, או
קום גלי *o kum gali*, he says, a חוצפה *chutzpah* look, what
type of stupid question. I'll give you a choice, you can either
go into גלות *galus* meaning get out of my yeshiva and never
show up here again or maybe literally you know go into like
as an עונש *onesh* on yourself. No, no, but they actually did
have an idea of being גולה *goleh*, you know, of actually putting
self-imposed exile as a type of a כפרה *kappara*. או קבל עליך
שמתא *o kabel alecha shamta*, or or we'll put you under נידוי
*nidui*, like a minor חרם *cherem*, but you got to do something
for that disrespectful question. Now I actually looked up פלימו *Plimo*, פלי
*peli* in ארמית *Aramis* means to mock or to actually make a
joke. So I wonder whether this was, you know, if this was
really his name or if he was really actually saying a joker
asked him this question, and we never get this name before. But
anyway the word פלי *peli* in ארמית *Aramis* does mean to sort
of, you know, make a joke. Anyway, says the גמרא *Gemara*, אדהכי
אתא הוא גברא *adehachi ata hu gavra*, so after רבי *Rabbi* got
so upset, a certain man came by the בית מדרש *beis medrash*.
אמר ליה Amar leih, *Amar lei*, and he said to רבי *Rabbi*,
איתיליד לי ינוקא דאית ליה תרי ראשי *Isyalid li yenuka d'is lei
srei rashi*, I just had a baby that had two heads, כמה
בעינא למיתב לכהן *kama be'ina lemisav le'kohen*? And it's a בכור Bechor,
*bechor*, how much do I have to give the כהן *kohen*? Now
of course you can't have two בכור Bechor *bechors*, you can only
have one בכור *bechor*, so what's the question? Because as we're going
to see the פסוק *pasuk* says you give five שקלים *shekalim* לגלגלת
*lagulgoles* for every head. So therefore it's one בכור *bechor* with two
heads. So obviously you only give for there's only one בכור *bechor*,
but here you'll give maybe ten שקלים *shekalim*. Okay. Now when you
have Siamese, you never will have this. No, you will have this.
Could be joined at the head, but they could be joined at
the hip or something. Joined at the chest. What, joined at the
chest?
Oh, the Abbey and Brittany's is like two.
They're both You're right. You're right.
They're basically joined at the head. Huh. Oh, okay. Huh. You're right.
There actually was a recently, the Siamese twins joined at the head.
It was a big surgery,
or first the Siamese twins in other places. It doesn't seem like
that's what it was. Right. Right. Okay.
Seems like
So let's take a look. I'm trying to remember if it explicitly
refers to it. Yeah, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
*Gemara* I don't know, I'd have to check that. Anyways, the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this. So he asks how much do I have
to give a כהן *kohen*? אתא הוא סבא תני ליה *Ata hu
saba tani lei*, so a certain elder came, and maybe רבי *Rabbi*
was a little too dumbfounded to respond. So a certain elder came
and taught a ברייתא *braisa* which says חייב ליתן לו י' סלעים
*chayav lisein lo yud sla'im*. This is not mocking רבי *Rabbi*'s case,
now you have a guy actually says it happened to be and
somebody actually said oh and we actually have codified it להלכה lehalacha
*lehalacha*. So רבי *Rabbi* was like so offended. First of all it's
an absurd case it never happens and like we shouldn't even be
discussing it theoretically להלכה *lehalacha*. Now you found out that actually both
things had happened in the case by בכור *bechor*.
Okay, so take let's take a look.
Okay,
so the גמרא *Gemara* says איני eini *eini*? So of course now
the גמרא *Gemara* has totally lost... the sort of I don't know
the irony and absurdity of all of it to make it a
pure like straight faced הלכה discussion. איני והתניא vehatanya רמי בר חמא
Rami bar Chama מתוך שנאמר mitoch shene'emar didn't רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama teach that since it says פדו תפדה בכור האדם pado
tifdeh bechor ha-adam שמע אני אפילו נטרף בתוך ל' shema ani afilu
nitraf betoch lamed and maybe even if the infant has is becomes
a טריפה? treifa? I'll read it like תוספות רש"י Tosafot Rashi has
a somewhat harder read of this. Maybe even if the infant cannot
survive, it's a טריפה, treifa, maybe you have a חיוב of פדיון.
pidyon. תלמוד לומר so the verse teaches אך חלק. ach chilak. However,
not in all cases. So why is that relevant? Presumably it's relevant
because it's saying that somebody who's born like this is not going
to be able to survive and it's basically like a טריפה. treifa.
So you've synopsized. So the answer's not clear if that was the
question. The answer is שאני הכא דבגולגולת תלה רחמנא. shani hacha de-begulgoleth
tala Rachmana. It says per head. So therefore okay that if you've
addressed other problems and you've said that he's viable then you can
ask do you give five or ten? But we have who says
we've addressed those other problems? Anyway, it's very funny, רבי doesn't have
the last word here. He got really upset and then right in
his face there was a real case and it was in a
ברייתא. So the גמרא ends with that. And we don't know how,
sadly Michael, we don't know which head he put תפילין on. Okay.
So now I never would have thought of that. I'm like you
know what happened to פלוני, Ploni, I feel bad for him.
Right, exactly. Okay. אמר מר. Amar mar. So okay so now going
back to what we said ידך זו קיבורת, yadecha zu kiboret, this
is the muscle. מנלן, minlan, where do you know it? דתנו רבנן.
detanu rabbanan. על ידך on your arm hand זו גובה שביד, zu
govah she-bayad, the higher place on the hand which is upper your
arm and maybe which is more visible and on the muscle which
is also high.
This also sounds like from like here.
Yeah well go yeah let's keep on going. אתה אומר זו גובה
שביד, atah omer zu govah she-bayad, the higher place of the hand
או אינו אלא על ידך ממש o einu ela al yadecha mamash
you literally hand. By the way יד, yad, Michael, does not just
mean this part, right? When we say ביד חזקה, beyad chazakah, right,
how's it go with
the outstretched arm, right, ובזרוע נטויה? uvizroa netuya? But יד חזקה yad
chazakah we presume doesn't just mean like the palm, like יד yad
normally can mean the whole hand, so but still nevertheless how do
we know או אינו אלא על ידך ממש? o einu ela al
yadecha mamash? But the גמרא clearly does have a more like specific
meaning which would be you know the palm of the hand. So
maybe that's what it means. אמר תורה, Amrah Torah, so the תורה
Torah says הניח תפילין של יד והניח תפילין של ראש. hinni'ach tefillin
shel yad vehinni'ach tefillin shel rosh. No, there's a
there's an implicit comparison. מה להלן בגובה שבראש, mah le-hallan begovah she-berosh,
the same way you put on the head is on the height
of the head. Now we don't know that, we said it before,
that it was you know that it was where the מקום שתינוק
רופס, mekom she-tinok rofais, which is like the higher part of the
head, not down here but higher up. Okay, we'll prove that in
a minute. אף כאן בגובה שביד. af kan begovah she-bayad. Here too
the higher place of the hand. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר, omer
by the way does anybody know what קראים Karaites do? Do they
put it like up here? Do they put it on the palm?
There is a קראים Karaite community in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, there are a
few thousands still around. Be interesting to know what they do.
Okay, interesting historically. I mean I think you might find this interesting
but the I forget who told me this but the that
from Hittite literature, you know like they had this literature like you
know about them it used to be that they used to in
war they used to like let's say take the axe or whatever
you want to call it and then chop at people and they
wrote you know in between the eyes, right, like it says בין
עיניך. Right, and then they actually saw like archaeologically that what they
did was
they actually got the the the skulls of their victims that were
actually in the place where you put on תפילין. Oh, interesting.
Meaning in their history they said בין עיניך we hit them between
their eyes but it was on the head. That's interesting, very nice,
יישר כוח. yishar koach. Okay. So okay so
where are we? No, I mean the bigger biggest evidence is even
from the תורה itself. לא תשימו קרחה בין עיניכם למת. lo tasimu
karcha bein einechem lamet. You can't make a bald spot for, right,
it says don't make a bald spot בין עיניכם למת, bein einechem
lamet, it's where hair grows from. Okay, so the גמרא says like
this. רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer... so אף כאן בגובה שביד. af kan
begovah she-bayad. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר אינו צריך, eino tzarich, you
don't need it from there. הרי הוא אומר harei hu omer והיה
לך לאות vehayah lecha le-ot ולך לאות ולא לאחרים לאות. ulecha le-ot
velo la-acherim le-ot.
Visible to you not to others. So if it's up here and
it's against your, you know, the side side of your body, people
don't see it. If down here on your palm it's very visible.
That is why by the way we cover our תפילין. Normally you
know you pull your sleeves down over your תפילין. The reason they
have those little black like paper boxes over the של יד shel
yad is you could say it's in order to just allow, you
know, so you don't have to put your sleeve down, but at
least what I understand is the reason they do that is because
if you pull your sleeve down over your תפילין the rubbing rubs
away the edges and it doesn't have that nice ריבוע. ribbu'a. So
you do this that to protect the תפילין.
Anyway, on the של יד shel yad they have like a little
plastic box that you put on top that they're not saying you
actually have to cover it with your sleeve. That the גמרא isn't
saying, it's in a place where it's more private, but we'll see
actually as the story continues that it is that there was a
story where it was covered, and that it was assumed to be
covered, and certainly להלכה they say based on this idea you should
that you're like obligated to, but ideally you should cover it based
on this idea of ולך לאות ולא לאחרים לאות. ulecha le-ot velo
la-acherim le-ot. Okay.
So the גמרא says רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak אומר אינו צריך, eino
tzarich, you don't need to, הרי הוא אומר harei hu omer ושמתם
את דברי אלה על לבבכם veshamtem et devarai eileh al levavchem on
your heart וקשרתם and you should bind them. שתהא שימה כנגד הלב,
she-tehey simah keneged halev, it should be placed near where the heart
is and that's higher up on the arm, which also I was
wondering... might be the nice explanation about why it goes on the
weak hand, or on the objectively left hand, not weak hand subjective,
but if you know based on that דרשה Drasha that it's all
as if just left because the left is closer to the heart,
right? I mean, the heart's in the center but it opens up
towards the left. Well they always say it's on the left anyway.
Right. Right. Okay, so if there's this idea of שימה כנגד הלב
Sima keneged haleiv that certainly is very consistent with the idea of,
you know, left. Okay. רבי חייא בר אבא... Rabbi Chiya bar Abba...
oh, or if you
want,
if you
want me to give you one final little דרש Drash on the
יד כהה, Yad keihah, why if you had two arms, one final
little דרש Drash on the יד כהה, Yad keihah, I could say,
you know, that part of the whole the idea is like if
it's about strength and, you know, it's about God's name and a
strong arm and so why not on the strong arm? But you
know, maybe the whole point is, it's sort of like the sort
of like the whole point of, you know, the תורה which is
like לא מרבכם כי אתם המעט מכל העמים, Lo merubchem ki atem
hame'at mikol ha'amim, it's not because of your natural strength. Meaning the
whole point of like the stories of בראשית Bereishit are, you know,
we're not the בכור, where it's like the second child is but
it's the second child because they're the more righteous one, you know,
is the one that is the chosen child. Right, everybody knows that
the whole theme of בראשית Bereishit is the usurpation of the right
of the primogeniture. There were a lot of big words there. But
anyway, right, you know, it was always like the second child that
because they, because God chooses not based on firstborn, you know, but
then God says בני בכורי ישראל. Beni bechori Yisrael. They're not my
firstborn but they have become the בכור because God choosing them. So
in a way, the fact that the יד כהה Yad keihah you
have the weak hand, it's not about internal, you know, physical strength,
but ultimately it's about, you know, connecting to God. It's about God,
you know, so to the תפילין being on that ultimately is what's
the what is significant is not only being chosen by God but
also, you know, being being somebody that's living up to, you know,
the moral and religious demands of what that relationship means.
You also spoke about, right? Yeah. So according to karaitecorner.org and karaitesight.org,
you're
looking up, yes, Karaites do not wear תפילין, they interpret them metaphorically.
Ah, what, you know, when and what, what I mean, what, they
have a תורה שבעל פה? Torah shebe'al peh? Except for... except for
the first pasuk! Okay,
it just shows you that everybody has a תורה שבעל פה, Torah
shebe'al peh, right? You can't say I'm a literalist, to here, here
be more literal is to interpret this as a metaphor. Okay, so
let's just read a little bit more. I know it's already 8:30
but let's just read a little bit more. גמרא says like this.
רבי חייא בר אבא בריה דרב אויא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba breih
de'Rav Avya מכווין ומניח להו להדי ליביה. Mechaven u'maniach lehu lehadi libeih.
He was very precise to make sure not just that it was
on the muscle, but it was actually directly opposite the heart. רב
אשי הוה יתיב קמיה דאמימר. Rav Ashi havah yasiv kamei d'Ameimar. Rav
Ashi was sitting in front of Ameimar. הוה ציירא בידיה, havah tzeira
biyadeih, he was, like he was, he had some type of a
wound on his arm.
וקמיחזין תפילין. v'kamichazyan tefillin. And his tefillin were... let me just check
the רש"י. Rashi. Hold
on, what... yeah, he had a wound, right? Oh, right, and then
he had torn his sleeve because he didn't want it to rub
against the wound. And because he had torn his sleeve, his tefillin
were now visible. וקמיחזין תפילין. v'kamichazyan tefillin. אמר ליה, לא סבר ליה
מר לכם אות ולא לאחרים אות? Lo savar leih mar lachem ot
v'lo l'acheirim ot? Don't you agree to the idea that it should
only be for you and not for others? Taking it very literally.
אמר ליה, במקום לכם אות איתמר. Bimkom lachem ot itmar. No, no,
no, it doesn't have to be literally covered, it just should be
in that place on the body. But again, because of the assumption
here of the question, there is this מנהג Minhag to, you know,
either have that plastic box or to pull your sleeve.
But they don't need to worry about it.
You don't need to, but you know, again, there's some value here,
meaning not a הלכה. Okay. גובה שבראש מנלן? Gova sheba'rosh minalan? How
do you know it's on the height of the head and not
literally between the eyes? דתנו רבנן, D'tanu rabbanan, בין עיניך זו גובה
שבראש, zu gova sheba'rosh, the height of the head. אתה אומר זו
גובה שבראש או אינו אלא בין עיניך ממש? Atah omer zu gova
sheba'rosh o eino ela bein einecha mamash? Literally between the eyes? נאמר
כאן בין עיניך ונאמר להלן לא תשימו קרחה בין עיניכם למת. Ne'emar
kan bein einecha v'ne'emar lehalan lo tasimu karcha bein eineichem lamet. Right?
Which is a pretty good proof. מה להלן בגובה שבראש מקום שעושה
קרחה, Mah lehalan b'gova sheba'rosh makom she'oseh karchah, the height of the
head here being defined as where you could make a bald spot,
where the hair grows from. אף כאן בגובה שבראש מקום שעושה קרחה.
Af kan b'gova sheba'rosh makom she'oseh karchah. Here too it's where the
hair grows from. רבי יהודה אומר אינו צריך. Rabbi Yehuda omer eino
tzarich. It's not needed. אמר תורה הנח תפילין ביד הנח תפילין בראש.
Amar Torah hanach tefillin beyad hanach tefillin barosh. Put it on the
hand, put it on the head. מה להלן במקום הראוי לטמא בנגע
אחד. Mah lehalan bimkom haraui letamei benega echad. So the same way
where it's on the hand, which is skin, so there's only one
נגע Nega that applies to skin... I mean there's one category that
applies, skin נגעים. Negaim Right. אף כאן במקום הראוי לטמא בנגע אחד.
Af kan bimkom haraui letamei benega echad. So it's a place on
the hair spot, there's only one category of נגעים Negaim. that applies,
hair נגעים. Negaim לאפוקי בין עיניך, L'apukei bein einecha, but if it
were literally between your eyes, דאיכא בשר ושיער. d'ika basar v'seiar. There's
both the skin that exists here and the hair of your eyebrow.
דאיכא שיער לבן ואיכא נמי שיער צהוב. D'ika seiar lavan v'ika nami
seiar tzahov. And therefore you could have the categories of the different
categories of נגעים because one would apply to the skin and one
would apply to the eyebrow. That should be the reason why we
don't need the other פלוגי? Plugai? because of course it's only where
there's one נגע. Nega. I don't know about the other פסוקים Psukim
are certainly, you know, pretty persuasive so we will end here and
actually from here on we now turn to ציצית tzitzit. to end,
although it's not the end of the פרק, Perek but now we
begin ציצית tzitzit and the next פרק perek, is going to be
devoted fully to ציצית. So with this we end תפילין. This is
the end תפילין.
Although it's not the end
of the פרק, perek but now we begin ציצית. And the next
פרק is devoted fully to ציצית. So with this we end, this
is ז׳ פ׳. zayin-pe. We now turn to the next chapter, פרק
ד׳, perek daled, which begins on דף לח עמוד א׳. daf lamed-chet
amud aleph. This chapter is entitled התכלת. Hatechelet. The reason it is
here in המנחות hamenachot is because of the conceptual link of מעכב.
me'akev. The משנה mishnah says: התכלת אינה מעכבת את הלבן והלבן אינו
מעכב את התכלת. Hatechelet einah me'akevet et halavan vehalavan eino me'akev et
hatechelet. The blue strings of the ציצית do not prevent the performance
of the מצוה mitzvah with the white strings, and the white strings
do not prevent the blue. Similarly, תפלה של יד אינה מעכבת של
ראש ושל ראש אינה מעכבת של יד. Tefilla shel yad einah me'akevet
shel rosh veshel rosh einah me'akevet shel yad. The hand-tefillin and the
head-tefillin are not מעכב me'akev one another. If you have only one,
you wear the one you have and fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of
that component. The גמרא asks: מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? What
is the source for this? דתנו רבנן. Detanu rabanan. For the Rabbis
taught in a ברייתא: והיה לכם לציצית, Vehaya lachem letzitzit, מלמד שמעכבין
זה את זה. melamed sheme'akvin zeh et zeh. This teaches that they
are indeed מעכב. me'akev. דברי רבי. This is the view of רבי.
וחכמים אומרים. Vechachamim omrim. However, the Sages say they are not מעכב.
me'akev. Our משנה mishnah reflects the opinion of the חכמים. Chachamim. מה
טעמא דרבי? Ma ta'ama deRabbi? What is the reasoning of רבי? אמר
קרא. Amar kra. The פסוק says והיה, which implies that it must
stay in its complete form.